A Guide to the Records of the Division of Motion Picture Censorship, 1926-1968
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Division of Motion Picture Censorship, 1926-1968
Library of Virginia
26515
57 cubic feet (62 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the Attorney General, 29 June 1966.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Board of Censors (forerunner to the Division) was established by H.B. 346 Chapter 257 of the Acts of Assembly approved March 15, 1922. The purpose of the act was to regulate motion picture films, provide a system of examination, approval and regulation of banners and posters and advertising material related to films and providing penalties for violation of the act. The law made it in effect illegal to sell or exhibit any commercial film that had not been officially approved and licensed by the Board.
The Board had the following requirements; (1) Movies could not be shown without a valid licenses or permit; (2) The Board was composed of three resident citizens of Virginia, appointed by the governor to 4- year terms subject to confirmation by the senate; (3) Criteria used to review films was based on if the film was "obscene, indecent, immoral, inhuman or is of such character that its exhibition would ten to corrupt morals or incite crime. A written explanation was required to explain why a license was not issued and a detailed description of rejected portions of a film; (4) The establishment of a fee structure (in order to receive a license to show movies in the state) of one dollar (1.00) per 1000 feet of film and fifty cents (.50) for each duplicate or copy of the original print; (5) On the 15th day of year an annual detailed report was to be submitted to the governor providing details such as receipts and disbursements and summaries of films examined.
On February 25, 1930 Chapter 49 of the Acts of Assembly Section 378A officially abolished the Board of Censors and established within the Department of Law the Division of Motion Picture Censorship. The Divisions' three censors had equal authority and were appointed and served at the pleasure of the Attorney General. The censors had to be "educated and experienced residents of Virginia". The three members of the division had the responsibility of voting a director from among their group. The function of the division was similar to that of the Board of Censors but with changes to accommodate the medium of "talkies" in film. The fee structure was increased at this time.
The Division of Motion Picture Censorship carried out its duties effectively until the decade of the 1960's when court decisions raised questions about the necessity of government to censor movies. Coupled with changing mores and liberal first amendment interpretations by the federal courts, the General Assembly passed legislation (HB 176) to repeal and stop funding the Division of Motion Picture Censorship effective June 30, 1966.
Scope and Content Information
Series I: LICENSE APPLICATIONS, 1926-1965 (14.5 cu. ft.) This series contains the actual applications for licenses to show and distribute films in the state of Virginia. The form includes the following information: date of license, title of movie or serial, names of lead characters, print number, duplicate number, reel footage, name of studio and address, notarized signature of designated representative for the studio and the date and signature of the notary public. The reverse side of the form may contain comments or remarks regarding the elimination of offensive parts of a film or the total rejection of a film due to its immoral content. Arranged alphabetically by film title.
Series II: LICENSES (REGULAR AND NON-REGULAR), 1954-1965 (10. 5 cu. ft.) This series contains two types of certificates, organized as Regular and Non-Regular Licenses. Both Regular and Non-Regular license certificates consists of two types of numbered forms. The license certificate entitled Licenses For Duplicates (Form 4) certifies that a motion picture studio is permitted to exhibit and display a film within the State of Virginia. The form contains the title of the movie, the date the certificate was issued, the amount of fee paid by the studio, serial number, print number and the signature of the Director of the Division of Motion Picture Censorship. The second form is entitled Copy of Application For Substitute Seal Original Receipted and Returned to Applicant (Form 8). This form gives the studio name, the title of the film, date issued and name of the Director. The form states that the movie studio is applying for a substitute seal to be attached to a print of the film previously censored and approved by the Division. The major difference between Regular and Non-Regular Licenses appears to be the arrangement order and time period. Regular Licenses are arranged by the prefix CS and cover the early 1950's to 1965 while the Non-Regular Licenses are arranged chronologically by serial number and cover the early 1960's. Arranged chronologically by serial number.
Series III: INDEX TO LICENSES AND APPLICATIONS, 1947-1965 (3.15 cu. ft.) This series contains 4x6 index cards that serve as an index to the non-Regular Licenses and the License Applications. The index includes the motion picture title, date license or application issued, studio releasing film and serial number. The pink index cards provide notations about the status of the film such as, whether a seal has been issued for a film, whether the film was eliminated or "rejected in toto" meaning it could not be shown in the state, and the conditional approval of a film with the seal of Virginia, issued at a later date. The index does not appear to apply to the Regular Licenses. Arranged alphabetically by film title.
Series IV: ATTENDANCE REPORT FOR EMPLOYEES, 1958-1965 (2.1 cu. ft.) This series contains 4x6 index cards that served as attendance forms for employees of the Division of Motion Picture Censorship. Each card has the name of the employee, day of the week, check mark for when the employee was present, or on sick/vacation leave and the signature of employees. Arranged alphabetically by board member.
Series V: THEATRE AND INSPECTOR LISTINGS, 1959-1965 (.35 cu. ft.) This series provides 4x6 index cards giving an alphabetical listing of movie theatres and separate listing for the name and address of inspectors along with the theatres they were responsible for monitoring. The movie theatres are organized by location of county, city and town. The index cards have notations for "Negro" inspectors and/or "Negro" owned theatres. The cards are divided into active (white color) and inactive (pink color) cards. There is a separate listing of index cards for inspectors of drive-ins. Arranged alphabetically by location.
Series VI: LISTING OF FILM TITLES, 1928-1957 (1 cu. ft.)This series offers a typed listing of movie titles, seal numbers, and notations of films eliminated and approved for viewing within the state. Some of the listings give only the date, movie title, serial number and the studio releasing the film. Arranged chronologically.
Series VII: FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1949-1960 (3.2 cu. ft.) This series consists of five volumes, one tablet, and a selection of financial reports that are Daily Billings (the form is entitled Film Record), which provide an overview of the financial housekeeping of the agency. There are three volumes entitled Cash Receipts dated 1950-1966 that provides an accounting ledger format with columns for the dates of transaction, studio names and assigned license number, fees for original and duplicate licenses, news reels charges and substitute seal fee along with totals for all columns. There are two volumes entitled Disbursements dated 1949-1950, an are organized in similar format as the Cash Receipts. The columns in these two volumes are identified as follows; Salaries, Wages, Repairs, Maintenance Service Contract, Travel, Transportation, Communications, Printing, Other Expenses, Office Supplies, Photographic, Supplies, Other Supplies, Office Equipment, Fire Insurance, Workmen's Compensation, Surety Insurance, Technical Subscriptions and Capitol Outlay. The one tablet entitled Office Cash Vouchers dated 1962, is an accounting booklet for the office petty cash fund. The columns headings in this tablet are for the Date of Transaction, Nature of Disbursement, Amount Paid, Totals, the Signatures for those authorized to approve payment, certification for the correct reimbursement and the checker of the transaction. The Daily Billings or Film Record dated 1960-1965, offers an insightful account of the amount of fees generated by charges applied to studios for original and duplicate prints and the seal issuance. The form contains the title of the movie, studio releasing film number of reels, total footage amount, print number, original seal number, duplicate seal number, substitute seal number and total amount of fees collected. Some reports have adding machine ticker tabulations attached to them. Arranged chronologically.
Series VIII: OFFICE ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS, 1924-1966 (1.5 cu. ft) This series contains the office voucher files for the Division of Motion Picture Censorship. The files provide information on financial management as well as procedures included in the operation and administration of the Division. There also are attendance reports for the Censors. Some of the topics include information on the Commonwealth's personnel act, procurement procedures and monthly report of monies collected by the Division. These records include a sampling of blank forms used by the Division during its' operation. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series IX: REPORT OF FILM CLERKS, 1960-1965 (1.2 cu. ft. )This series gives a form entitled Film Clerk's Report. The form consists of multiple pages with the following categories and headings: Title (movie title), Exchange (studio name) Number of Reel, Footage, Print Number, Original Seal Number, Duplicate Print Number, Duplicate Seal Number, and Substitute Seal. Not all categories on the form contain information. Arranged chronologically by date.
Series X: ANNUAL REPORTS, 1924-1965 (.2 cu. ft.) This series contains the yearly reports for the Censorship Division as submitted to the Governor. The reports provide a detailed narrative and statistical breakdown of the activities for the fiscal year. The first report reflects in detail the standard used in the elimination and /or rejections of certain films. The main purpose for censorship was to prevent the display of "obscene, indecent, immoral or inhuman films of such character that their exhibition would tend to corrupt moral(s) or incite crime". The earlier reports (roughly 1924-1935) offer a descriptive narrative account of the activities of the Board. The reports of the 1920's document the improprieties of certain comic films of the day. One report states that "directors seem willing to violate all the refinements and all conventions in order to get a laugh!" There are descriptions of total scenes cut from films along with examples given of specific movies and the reasons for the "slicing". The report of 1927- 1928 highlights the advent of the new technology in motion pictures, "the talkies". Among the concerns of the Board about the new technology was the cost of purchasing new projectors that would allow viewing and editing of synchronized films. In the Annual Report of 1931, comments are made about the "great onslaught of gang pictures". This "problem" was not seen as vital for Virginia as for the "northern states where the foreign population is greater". None the less the Censors' considered gangster movies fostered a "disagreeable situation" that members of the Censors' hoped producers of this genre of film would "tone down in the future". In the 1941 report, advances in technology are highlighted with the introduction of a new projector known as the "Juke Box" that used (16) sixteen-millimeter film. Once again, the report documents concerns about getting state appropriations for the purchase of new equipment. The reports of 1943-1944 make note of the surprise in the increase in the number of films due to the fact of restrictions placed on raw materials (including film) during World War II. The reports of later years (roughly 1947-1965) are more statistical and less narrative in composition. The statistical tables give a numerical breakdown of films. The headings on the report are Totals for the Years, Elimination, Rejections, Receipts, Disbursements and Revenue Refunds. The financial statements provide the amount of fees collected and turned over to the state treasurer. Often, they will include disbursement of operating expenses and capital outlay. Arranged chronologically.
Series XI: ELIMINATION RECORDS, 1945-1965 (.4 cu. ft.) This series gives the form sent to the studios documenting in writing the eliminated scenes or cuts from feature films. The form contains the name and address of the studio, title of movie, a brief and graphic description of the scene cut from the original movie and the signatures of the Director of the Division of Motion Picture Censorship and the authorized agent for the studio. The form usually has triplicate copies and sometimes includes an attachment of correspondence between Censors and studio executives. Arranged chronologically.
Series XII: CORRESPONDENCE (OUTGOING AND INCOMING), 1958-1966 (.8 cu. ft.) This series consists of carbon copies of letters mailed from the various Directors' of the Division of Motion Picture Censorship and the other Censors. The letters cover a wide range of topics including the discussion with studio executives regarding censorship decisions made by the Division. The files include information on the daily operations of the division along with the records from two prominent former directors, Mrs. Lollie C. Whitehead and Mrs. Russell F. Wagers. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series XIII: CORRESPONDENCE (ACTIVE THEATRES/DRIVE-INS), 1957-1965 (2.3 cu. ft.) This series gives copies of outgoing and incoming letters between the Director of the Division and theater and drive-in owners of viable theaters within the state from 1957 to 1965. The correspondence mainly consists of the Director looking for recommendations for the names of individuals to work as inspectors, to view films and verify that the state seal had been appropriately applied to the print. The files are organized by the name of the theater and include the theaters' location. The files have special notations for "Negro"only theaters and inspectors. There are also report forms that list the number of admission card issued to an inspector. Arranged alphabetically by name of theater.
Series XIV: CORRESPONDENCE (INACTIVE-CLOSED THEATRES), 1957-1965 (2.3 cu. ft.) This series offers the outgoing and incoming letters between the Director of the Division of Motion Picture Censorship and the owners of theaters and drive-ins that were no longer in existence. The correspondence mainly consists of inquiries by the Director for the name of inspectors for the theaters and notification to the Director that the theater or drive-in is no longer in operation. Some files may contain returned admission cards issued to inspectors for their free admittance into the theaters. These files may include an index card with the name and address of the inspector assigned to a specific theater. Arranged alphabetically by name of theater.
Series XV: GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE AND CONTROVERSIAL FILMS, 1922-1966 (2.7 cu. ft.) This series combines general correspondence of the agency director and correspondence regarding films that were eliminated for viewing within the state of Virginia. The correspondences consist of letters mailed to movie distributors, court documents as well as correspondence from the state's Attorney General. The series includes selected promotional movie posters, examples of advertisements in movie industry trade magazines and scripts of some of the movies listed. There are recurring issues that caused grave concern for the Censors. Among those issues of concern are films that depict "miscegenation". It is noted in the records that sexual relations between Black and white people were against the law and transgresses "rules of propriety". In general, films that displayed sexual content were strictly censored or rejected in toto. In one report the suggested that "some of the bedroom scenes are particularly disgusting and are calculated to shock even the most vulgar." Violent films and movies emphasizing racial situations were rejected due to concerns that these movies might incite people to riot. The Censors rejected a 1947 movie entitled "The Burning Cross," (a film portraying the Ku Klux Klan in a negative light) because of the films' tendencies to "excite prejudices and intense emotions thereby reviving controversies and disputes that the Censors' believes presently to be quiet, and not now occupying the public attention". The Censors' insisted that the film be banned despite objections from religious leaders and civil rights organizations such as the N.A.A.C. P., which wanted the film shown to help counter the "more than a score of years of propaganda" in support of the K.K.K. in the movie industry. The civil rights organization was perplexed by the Board's action since they had supposedly allowed the showing of "The Birth of a Nation", a film that portrayed the Klan in a most favorable light. In, 1924 a movie entitled "A Son of Satan" "released by a colored concern" was banned in toto because it portrayed "a mulatto whose villainies were inherited by his white forefathers". Arranged alphabetically.
Series VI: CENSORSHIP REPORTS, 1960-1965 (.8 cu. ft.) This series documents the work of censorship boards in other states and Canada. The format of the reports vary however, all the reports provide movie titles, scenes deleted from movies, total number of prints and the studio responsible for producing the film. Arranged chronologically by date of report.
Contents List
- License applications, 1926-1965
  This series offers the actual application for license to show and distribute films in the state of Virginia. The form contains the following information: date of license, title of movie or serial, names of lead characters, print number, duplicate number, reel footage, name of studio and address, notarized signature of designated representative for the studio and the date and signature of the notary public. The reverse side of the form may contain comments or remarks regarding the elimination of offensive parts of a film or the total rejection of a film due to its immoral content.
  Arranged alphabetically by film title.
  - License applications, A-Ac, 1937-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - License applications, Ad-Ah, 1934-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - License applications, Ai-Ali, 1934-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - License applications, Alj-Alz, 1936-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - License applications, Am-An, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - License applications, Ao-Arh, 1935-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - License applications, Ari-Art, 1936-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - License applications, As-Ay, 1931-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - License applications, B-Bac, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - License applications, Bad-Ban, 1930-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - License applications, Be-Beh, 1932-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - License applications, Bei-Beo, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - License applications, Bep-Bh, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - License applications, Bi-Bij, 1933-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - License applications, Bik-Bk, 1932-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - License applications, Bl-Bln, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - License applications, Bo-Bor, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - License applications, Bos-Boy, 1934-1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - License applications, Br-Bril, 1934-1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - License applications, Brim-Bru, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - License applications, Bu-By, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - License applications, C-Cal, 1935-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - License applications, Cam-Cap, 1933-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - License applications, Car-Cas, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - License applications, Cat-Cav, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - License applications, Ce-Che, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - License applications, Chi-Chu, 1934-1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - License applications, Ci-Ck, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - License applications, Cl-Cn, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - License applications, Co-Col, 1933-1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - License applications, Com-Cop, 1935-1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - License applications, Cor-Cq, 1931-1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - License applications, Cr-Cri, 1934-1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - License applications, Crj-Cz, 1931-1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - License applications, Da-Daq, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - License applications, Dar-Dd, 1932-1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - License applications, De-Der, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - License applications, Des-Det, 1934-1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - License applications, Dev-Dia, 1936-1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - License applications, Dic-Dob, 1933-1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - License applications, Doc-Dom, 1933-1956 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - License applications, Don-Dor, 1935-1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - License applications, Dot-Dq, 1935-1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - License applications, Dr-Dt, 1935-1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - License applications, Du-Dz, 1935-1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - License applications, E-Eh, 1934-1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - License applications, Ei-Em, 1936-1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - License applications, En-Et, 1932-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - License applications, Ev-Ez, 1934-1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - License applications, F-Far, 1934-1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - License applications, Fas-Fh, 1935-1956 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - License applications, Fi-Fil, 1934-1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - License applications, Fin-Fiv, 1935-1956 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - License applications, Fix-Fly, 1936-1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - License applications, Fm-For, 1932-1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - License applications, Fos-Fre, 1935-1956 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - License applications, Fri-Fru, 1937-1957 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - License applications, Fu-Fuz, 1934-1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - License applications, Ga, 1934-1955 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - License applications, Gb-Ge, 1926-1956 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - License applications, Gh-Gk, 1934-1956 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - License applications, Gl-Gom, 1934-1956 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - License applications, Gon-Goy, 1933-1956 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - License applications, Gr-Grh, 1934-1956 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - License applications, Gri-Gyp, 1934-1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - License applications, H-Han, 1931-1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - License applications, Hap-Haz, 1934-1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - License applications, He-Heo, 1934-1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - License applications, Hep-Hey, 1934-1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - License applications, Hi-Hil, 1930-1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - License applications, Him-Hm, 1934-1956 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - License applications, Ho-Hol, 1934-1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - License applications, Hom-Hos, 1935-1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - License applications, Hot-How, 1934-1956 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - License applications, Hu-Hz, 1934-1956 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - License applications, I-Il, 1932-1956 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - License applications, Im-Ino, 1935-1955 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - License applications, Inp-Ir, 1934-1956 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - License applications, Is-Ito, 1934-1955 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - License applications, Itp-Iz, 1934-1955 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - License applications, Ideal Pictures (A-W), 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - License applications, Ja-Jav, 1934-1955 (Box 4, Folder 18)